so this is the beginning of the satiana
suta this is majaya
10 so I have heard at one time the
Buddha was staying in the land of the
kurus near the Kuru town named K sadama
there the Buddha addressed the buikus
buikus bante they replied the Buddha
said this bicus this is the path that
leads squarely to the purification of
beings to getting past sorrow and
lamentation to make an end of suffering
and upset to accomplishing the method
and to realizing nibana namely the four
establishments of recollection what for
here abiku abides maintaining
perspective of the body concurrently
with with the body diligent aware and
recollected having dispelled longing and
upset in regard to the world he abides
maintaining perspective of feelings
concurrently with feelings diligent
aware and recollected having dispelled
longing and upset in regard to the world
he abides maintaining perspective of the
Mind concurrently with the Mind diligent
aware and recollected having dispelled
longing and upset in regard to the world
he abides maintaining perspective of
phenomena concurrently with phenomena
diligent aware and recollected having
dispelled longing and upset in regard to
the
world so how do you practice that concretely is
but you would have to start by
understanding the concurrency that is a
common threat with all the four
establishments s by
collection and perhaps we can clear up
from the outset that um virtue and
sensory straint are already
prerequisites doesn't to mention that
again so assuming that that is
understood then one needs to understand
that uh concurrent attention as a as a
principle that all these Sati patama
have in
common yeah because I think I mentioned
in one of the previous ones
that it's easy for people to think of
satiana as absorption or focusing
because they overemphasize the
body but it's talking there about these
four aspects and and
feelings like it says if you read
further it says
um because feelings then in the same
along the same lines feelings are
interpreted Sensations but if you look
further in the suta it says you have
feelings of the flesh feelings not of
the flesh so that right from the
outset disqualifies the interpretation
of feelings as Sensations which means
like if you have something that's not of
the flesh something that's not like in
your knees or in your back or or in your
belly uh by definition that's not
something you'll be able to focus on and
as it says there it's uh well as I
translated it's a maintaining
perspective um so
we could maybe ask uh why does it say
there that these four foundations of
that these four foundations of
recollection would help you to transcend
suffering and transcend sorrow
lamentation and uh you know overcoming
upset and longing in regard to the
world if it's not FOC because of course
you you uh you will
overcome uh longing in in all states by
just replacing what you perceive with
something else uh like you you kind of
uh fix the mess that you have in the
room by not being there to begin with
you just go to another room and then you
don't have to see what what's there yeah
but which means that fundamentally you
don't really fix it exactly you're just
sticking your head in the sand basically
but so if so if it's not that then how
does this actually help to to transcend
up yeah so how does maintaining
perspective in these four distinct ways
and s lamentation pain grief and despair
that's the question right yeah so that's
that kind of I mean I guess little
insert before we really delve into that
question um because it talks about these
four establishments and it says having
put aside um was it longing and despair
um so that it kind
of the way I read that is it it kind of
says that have like the putting that
aside is almost your gateway into this
practice Yeah because always in the
sutas um there's many sutas that say
that practice of mindfulness is preceded
by sense restraint and sense restraint
as defined it's exactly the same uh term
in po that talks about uh longing and
upset like not grasping signs and
features means that you won't be
overcome with longing and upset
regarding the objects of the six senses
and that's like the prerequisite for
satiana it's not the result of Sati time
so in other words you you you need to
already not be doing this as a form of
management because you have dealt with
the course longing and upset beforehand
through sensor restraint so not you're
not doing if you skip that aspect then
automatically this will just become a
way of like how do I replace this or get
rid of it as quickly as possible and
then you're not really maintaining
perspective you're kind of just
replacing one thing with another but the
perspective remains equally
muddled so that's a lot of people might
go into this practice looking for the
way out of longing and upset but
actually overcoming longing and upset to
some degree is kind of your that's
that's the work that needs to be done
before you can even really think about
set properly yeah
yeah that's uh I think samai 46.6 we can
put it in the description that talks
about how yes uh mindfulness is preceded
by sensor strength when you already
established in sensor strength then you
can practice the force of but so having
having said that then how does that um
cement and and
fully uh yeah establish your mind in
Freedom from any kind of
suffering or you could ask it the other
way how does not having
mindfulness make you suffer
so what's what's longing and
upset what's uh what is sorrow is it
just objects that come to you
small like my attitude toward this
subject and more specifically like based
on what attitude would there be so and
despair and so on like craving I'm
craving for things to be L the way it is
just wantan things to be
different and it doesn't say Destro
praying longing and upset it's
more um kind of
um kind of
those
not continually acting out of these
Tendencies so that's like that's not to
say there won't still
be inclinations towards old habits but
it's it's not just like oh you know I
still sometimes like have the thought
that I should whatever smoke a cigarette
like gosh that means I haven't kind of I
haven't gotten it yet you know maybe a
few more years that'll eventually kind
of wear out I've noticed over the past
few years you know you get into that
kind of stuff but it's like the the
setting at down to something you should
be able to do immediately yeah and and
you look at the description of
mindfulness of the mind and it doesn't
say he doesn't have passion he doesn't
have a verion it's says when it when
it's there he knows it as such and in
itself that's an establishment of
perspective because so what what I was
trying to get at is yes so it's the
craving that makes these objects a
problem which means that if you yes if
you replace the objects the craving
won't be there because like the push for
the craving is not there anymore but
that doesn't mean you're not liable to
the craving so then if you instead of
going at that route you
realize it's through lack of perspective
that craving comes to be it's not
through just in in itself kind of this
comes to me or something it's
immediately when you don't have
perspective you act out on some level
even if you have you're establishing
sensor strength and so on
um you so longing and upset like you're
not acting out of it anymore but but the
the perversion of of perception you
could say or the perversion of the wrong
order of seeing things is still there so
the feeling that you might be having for
example we could take that example as so
as to sort of um illustrate the
principle in a way that people probably
not familiar with because it's usually
the body that's that's emphasized as I
just said so let's say you have a
unpleasant feeling that's enduring right
now so you're established in virtue
you're not out of it but
um if you're not aware that there is an
unpleasant feeling enduring for me right
now as s says automatically you will
be on some level inclining towards
either getting rid of it or or indulging
in it whatever it wants you to do you
you should have at least welcome that
direction even if you're not doing it uh
physically or verbally so when you
see actually not just how do I get rid
of this but no there is a feeling
unpleasant feeling enduring in this
experience and I maintain perspective of
that that
perspective in itself prevents you from
acting out of it but you need to to some
extent that's why the S to say faith
needs to come first faith is a fa as a
faculty it even comes before mindfulness
or before recollection because because
um if you haven't taken it on faith that
that is the middle way that it is just
this maintaining a perspective that will
truly uproot the underlying Tendencies
of craving then your mind will convince
you like no no no I have to deal with it
I have to do something about it yeah you
you will be going with your old habit
which is trying to deal with feelings
yeah can we say like just to see if I
understood what you say like so the
feeling is there regardless we like it
or not but ignorance in regard to it
it's something that we actively engage
with that direction of ignoring that
feeling you have a say in it yeah well
we have a say in it but it's if we don't
see this thinging it's because we
ourself engage in that direction of
ignorance yeah yeah yeah so the the more
you act out then the the harder it
becomes to recognize it the more the
ignorance increases uh but that's why
then it says uh in
the dependent origination
uh formula or or series of steps it says
with ignorance there is activity there
is acting out obviously of the wrong
kind not like just anything in general
it's all it takes for these UNH
wholesome things to be there is not
seeing and and not seeing in this proper
sense of this you could say it's like um
lack of clarity of these General aspects
of your experience makes you um descend
onto the particulars of the experience
so descending onto particulars is what
un wholesomeness is MH in of itself like
even if it's like the right ideas about
dhama or or something like that the fact
that you are just absorbed in that and
you don't see the more General uh
component of that experience then and
there I means you will be acting out of
craving yeah and so since as and since
being with the particulars is the
problem there then body as a satiana
cannot be a particular feeling as a
saatana cannot be a particular sensation
mind as a particular or mood cannot be
random thoughts that you happen to have
and dhama as a as general phenomenon
cannot be anything particular so they
all come with let's say a relative
totality and that needs to be discerned
which is the perspective and perhaps we
can find out why when that perspective
is established how how when there is
that totality when one establishes one's
mind that way why there is no room for
craving then to
interfere how is that why why is it that
when that perspective is lost and you
dwell on the particulars that that by
definition means craving which is a
suffering well the thing is you wouldn't
be able to um explain like why in a sort
of external sense as if you get out of
your experience and then examine how it
happens it's like at any given time you
are either absorbed in the particulars
or you are established in the right
perspective so you would get to see that
then um again you would need to have
faith in in that the Buddha is saying
these things are overcome through
perspective not through directly
tackling them head on CU that's when you
get into well you fall from the middle
way as a su to say as as the first the
Samaya says when you push forward uh you
you get carried away by the flood when
you stand still you sink so pushing
forward means like I'm trying to get rid
of this I'm trying to replace it with
something else and then standing still
is like you just give up everything just
I don't make any effort I just relax and
choice choiceless awareness or something
like that but no it's it is an effort
and uh there is no right mindfulness
without right effort because it's that's
the the how the path works but it's not
an effort in the sense of changing the
content of what you're experiencing
it's seeing that General nature that's
that sits behind that content and as you
said the body has to be understood in
that on that level as well because the
body is like that's actually the purpose
of uh breathing for example uh which is
the very first uh uh item that comes up
in the mindfulness of the body it's it
breathing is that General thing that's
always there mhm like regardless of the
content of your experience the one thing
that you have that you know for sure if
you're still alive is that breathing
will be there underneath everything else
that's happening so then that un absorbs
you from these particulars of your
experience and um and it's actually like
precisely the point not to focus on it
because something that's
General necessarily is defined by its
relation to particulars so if you focus
on it you turn it into a new particular
so it's not the context anymore and then
something else will be the background to
that and and the the point as well is is
like perspective um it's not even something
perspective um it's not even something
that you can do every second if it's
really a perspective um it it's by
definition something that you establish
it for a moment and then it will endure
for who knows how long so let's say yes
uh I was distracted I called myself
acting out of un wholesome States and I
remember oh there's an Pleasant feeling
here which is sort of that pressure
that's directing me to do these things
and then um you establish that and then
different thing different things will
start to come up in your mind your mind
will start to be thinking about other
stuff but you still haven't completely
forgotten that that unpleasant feeling
is there which means that those thoughts
that are coming up they are not anymore
um well founded upon that ignorance so
they're not really thoughts of UNH
wholesome nature of trying to act out of
that feeling so even though that feeling
is
there uh you're not acting out of it and
to that extent there is Purity like the
other suta that we that we read like
even if you have the hindrances present
internally but on the level of thought
you're not acting out of them the Buddha
defines that as Purity actually that's
right yeah uh so that's the the
principle and then the same happens with
the with the with the mind with the
moods uh even if you you have a mind of
passion mind of aversion mind of
distraction seeing that and maintaining
perspective of that
means for that period of time as long as
that perspective is there any thought
that comes because of the perspective
not because of its content in of itself
will be wholesome it will not be um
proliferating that uh that uh those un
wholesome States and then through not
feeding them in that way MH not by
directly them as I said then eventually
they will dissipate so then um then you
will not even have the the lustful mind
or aers mind or whatever yeah so when
one maintains perspective in this way is
One automatically not feeding those
thoughts or is there something else that
needs to happen
there what do you well you were just
saying like when you maintain
perspective then by thoughts that
content doesn't matter anymore they will
will be wholesome because you maintain
perspective M I'm just making sure is
that it is it just a question of
maintaining perspective well practically
speaking it is but I mean uh
theoretically speaking it is but
practically like the mind again will be
trying to like scare you or or um
convince you that no no what do I do
next or something like that yeah so I
wanted to go into that because that can
be come quickly an obstacle and this is
why you mentioned I think earlier that
Faith Comes even before the mindfulness
because um it's not there's not going to
be a tangible result that one is
actually not immediately at least that
one is wearing away now let's say the
causes or the origin of suffering where
factually one is so that right that's
where the faith comes in which is why
the understanding is important and
perhaps also we should then clear up
that faith in the Buddhist teaching is
based on the right understanding not on
hoping that will be some results yeah
yeah Faith needs to come with with
discernment like like you you have faith
because to some extent you have seen
that these things are beneficial or
wholesome but um but yeah so when you
are let's say you as I said before you
you have an unpleasant feeling enduring
or you have a um some kind of restless
mood or something like that and uh
initially Yes you heard the instruction
and you just try to okay this is the
general aspect of my experience is
present now I'm not acting out of it I
leave it
there and then 5 seconds
later oh but no no no I need to I need
to I need to I remember that that sua
said I'm supposed to do this I'm
supposed to replace this thought with
that one and what not and then you um
you had it for a moment and you fall
from it because because of your own um
well you couldn't sustain that
perspective you were captivated by that
how you thought basically yeah yeah you
didn't manage to sustain that
perspective even in face of something
that was trying to distract you and
that's basically how the hindrances work
it's like that's why they say they're
weakener of of PA weaken of wisdom it's
like they take you away from from from
the right perspective that you might
have had for moments so so it's it's um
learning to um to see that that's really
all that matters what matters is that
there that that perspective is presently
established and then you will you will
you will not even it's not possible that
you will see
yourself the perspective like shrinking
as if as if you were looking at another
person from the outside no you basically
find that you've lost it yeah exactly
you you realize oh wait I was again
acting out of that feeling which means I
forgot it I forgot the perspective and
then you bring it back and then um
what's going to happen is like you keep
doing that and at some point like it
becomes impossible for you to to to even
forget the feeling even with making no
effort to think about it yeah but that
will then be the result so initially one
needs to recognize that one fell from
that perspective and in a sense the the
the the recognition that one fell away
from it is the reestablishment of it
it's not that something else needs to
happen if that if that understanding was
there before when you realize it's gone
that realization is the and if you still
have a again the the the faith to see no
that's what matters I'm not going to
give in the impulse to do more than this
and start replacing and and absorbing
myself into
specifics then yes you bring it back um
but practically speaking it's always
going to be a little bit messier than
that you will be falling into no no uh
like rehearsing ideas to to kind of the
right ideas but because now you're again
attending them at the expense of the
perspective out of like the need for
that intellectual Clarity which gives
you emotional satisfaction as well you
will be forgetting that no no actually
what matters is is the the general
aspect not this content of the right
ideas that I read from the SAS or
something like that um but the reason
why I was saying that is because then
that's that's that's how you get to see
when the suas say um the the persistent
development of the forti panas is the
unification of mind is the is samadi
meaning like when you're so clear about
this let's say nature of the feeling
that's enduring in your experience that
you cannot forget it that's why then you
you were free from the five hindrances
because all of them were um they were
weakening your perspective but at the
same time they themselves were rooted in
lack of perspective so it's like a
vicious circle and then when you have
that established
um as the Buddha said like whether you
whether you sit stand walk lie down
basically all that matters is that you
keep in mind these phenomena are there
as it says in the maima 19 the two types
of thought these these things are there
and um that's when it's always in the
sutas when it talks about samadi it says
the Mind becomes composed or established
inally and that internal aspect is
exactly that it's it's these General
aspects of your experience because
what's external is always the six senses
like the objects of the six senses even
your thoughts yes even if they're the
right thoughts and the right Reflections
but you're again treating them as
objects those things are external and so
when the Mind becomes established
internally means it's this underlying
basis for everything else and then the
content of your experience doesn't
matter anymore because all of it will be
in and of itself pure because the
perspective is
there yes that's the shift rather than
trying to sort out the content which is
all impermanent anyway so that's going
to be endless this practice is about
maintaining perspective upon that and
that's that's what it's meant with
uprooting things it's like it's not um
some sort of switch inside of you that
you flip and then these things don't
arise anymore it's you aboot them
because it's like
it's kind of like um like a
dark like these things can only happen
in the dark un wholesome States that's
what actually the Buddha compared uh
wisdom with light and ignorance with
Darkness yes and these things can only
happen when there is Darkness if there's
light it just
can't yeah certain things can only grow
in the dark yeah when you switch of the
light they with away yeah yeah so that's
exactly what it is light not in the
sense of new object that sort of pop
into your experience which in itself
doesn't mean anything because you don't
have perspective over that and you can
very much still be having craving
towards these new objects doesn't matter
how special or extraordinary they are
but in this sense like these things that
that are already there even in your most
ignorant days and when you were fully
captivated by by uh sense objects and
sensuality the fact remained that the
body was the background of your
experience you you had a feeling present
at that time the mood was there and
there were phenomena there as well so in
that sense the it's the like the dhama
the path that the the Buddha didn't
create not even internally like it's
just the path that it was already there
that freedom was already accessible and
possible simply because there are things
in your experience that it don't depend
on your choice like they're there anyway
MH and it's these four found conditions
of mindfulness so
of course um as as we uh mentioned the
last few talks as well there can only be
right mindfulness with the Right View so
so you can't just take up these things
and just start doing them but at the
same time you can take it as an exercise
in developing Right View if you take it
as an exercise of okay not just how do I
do
this uh not just like let me do this but
uh asking yourself how do I how am I
supposed to PR
continu clarify and upgrading your of
that practice then that can be a way to
approach the Right View which is
understanding the the noil path yeah so
by making an effort to understand what
these for saatana are and how they will
bring about the destruction of craving
one might actually come to see for
oneself yeah you would see the for Noble
Truths you would see the sensation of
craving as a result of that yes um so so
it's that's why it's useful but it's
it's that shift and attitude where most
of us when we hear about Buddhism it's
just like okay I heard this instruction
now let me do this but you never
question yourself as to the fact that
even though like no matter how good the
instruction from the person is you
yourself will have assumptions regarding
how to practice this which will make it
wrong for you because of the because of
the attitude that gets introducing
craving where there shouldn't be and so
on so if you don't make an effort to to
um Rectify that first and you just start
doing it with however with with
whichever attitudes you had from the
start then it's not going to lead to
what it was supposed to be yeah so you
cannot be just take a pragmatist
approach and from the beginning just you
know put some musle on it and and do it
that's going to be too easy yeah and and
it's not even what's like what works for
you at the moment because as the Buddha
said it's it's like what will naturally
happen if you just emphasize what makes
me more calm what makes me more peaceful
it's just going to be the way it makes
you feel so it was just going to be an
Endeavor of how do I never feel
displeasure and as Buddha said um
there's dis pleasure there's pleasure
that should be cultivated pleasure that
should not be cultivated displeasure
that should be cultivated displeasure
that shouldn't be cultivated so in other
words it's not that all displeasure you
immediately get rid of but but if you
take like you said a pragmatist approach
what that's going to result in is it's
just like how do I not feel this
pleasure ever yeah which means that
you're already reacting to feeling
basically yeah and and you're not
establishing that background of like no
no it's not like what I feel mhm which
is content it's the fact that I know
feeling as the background of all of my
actions which prevents those actions
from being rooted and craving yeah
perhaps you're going to speak a bit more
about understanding this background
rightly which is just synonymous with
context and perspective and now occur to
me there's this one discourse where s
was talking about this and he says I
just decide in the morning to put on a
coat or a jacket and then in the in the
midday I put on another coat and then in
the evening I can put on yet another
jacket or another coat and that was a
simile for how he was practicing these
establishments of of of mindfulness so
he just decides to dwell in one of these
Sati patana and I think that simile is
quite accurate like a cod is something
wider right it's it's something that
sort of envelops you and that you find
yourself within and and and you can put
on different codes right right so you
have now we have body feeling mind
phenomena there like four different
backgrounds but you do need to sort of
have the intention oh okay I'm going to
stick with this one now and establish
that as a perspective and then in a
sense it doesn't really matter which of
the four if you do it right because it's
the principle that that that matters the
principle being the that they all offer
a perspective upon the content which is
present and they cannot be independent
of that right the the background is not
independent of the content which is
present but dwelling on that background
knowledge is the perspective that then
prevents the craving from further
proliferating it's the principle of
concurrency as was said before yeah and
that's why then yes the foras are the
kind of most
um you could say standard or formulaic
description of right mindfulness but the
sutas are full of other ways like um the
Brahma viharas you have the
um uh perception
of dispassion perception of non Delight
um it says like perspect perspective of
the satisfaction of
food um you have these um perceptions of
the forest uh some times it would even say
forest uh some times it would even say
um like oh you just contemplate the root
of a tree you expand your mind using the
perception of the root of a tree see
that's also wider then from the root of
a tree you expand it to uh the forest
then from the forest you expand it to
the Village from the village you expand
it to the country and all of these are
essentially the same thing it's just
contextualizing yeah what whatever is
happening in your mind with that broader
thing that's already there it doesn't
depend on you maintaining it no and
that's actually why it's it's it's
peaceful because that perspective then
it's not like I'm doing this no every
moment you are recollecting that you're
ceasing to ignore it that there's always
a possibility of establishing a step
back quote unquote which is this context
which which is what puts the perspective
upon what's happening right now sheds
light on it
without you needing to to put it there
something that was already there you
just recognize it so that's the
principle if it feels like I'm I'm just
doing this and maintaining this that's
not the right the right way even if the
idea about it is right but it means
you're not seeing it really as something
that's in your experience you're sort of
fabricating it yeah so you're not
fabricating it but the effort has to be
in recollecting that it is already there
so perhaps we can discuss now um some
let's say um ways that will help to not
fall away from this which practically
speaking will mean like how was I'm
going to recollect this right so we have
clear cleared up to to some degree this
congruency and the perspective but one
will be falling away from it so how to
practically not fall away from that
that's the first thing yeah keep your
keep your
virtue don't act out in the like super
coarse obvious
ways also don't act out in the less
obvious ways
either and then how come after that
also don't act out of the question all
right what
now well we say
that one will like fall out for this
middle way like many time like many many
times and at some point he might feel
like oh I'm not going to follow away
anymore and then I can relax but that is
already falling so instead of trying to
like what to put that I think it's like like
what to put that I think it's like like
The Bu use an image like it's like the
kind of the guy who guard the car is
kind of fitting them to not go into the
crops and as when they don't go into the
crops he don't like just lie down and
fall asleep he like he lie down he can
relax but he keep on eyes on them he
keep like he still like he can kind of
to some degree relax but you still have
to have in mind that as long as he's not
free from the liability from these
things to happening that can still to
some degree happen so I'm still sitting
there watching my cow and but it's still
much more peaceful
before so being vigilant I would say is
kind of one one I kind of manage to
understand like this kind of
recollection of this kind of Direction
between content and context is to kind
of every time you fall to come back but
one is not falling back to still
watching it yeah because because if you
understood it right you would realize
that it's again these things are already
in your experience so if it feels like
being vigilant or maintaining it is is
like painful or or or like it's a burden
then you you haven't understood the
properly because it's like actually your
your act of forgetting about these
things come second to these things
already being there so so in that sense
it's it's
um even you're forgetting is kind of
like irrelevant because it's it's
fundamentally still there relevant in
the sense that of qualify of course
doesn't mean like you're you're
Justified and forgetting but what it
means is like if you emphasize again the
aspect of no no it's only there when I
am thinking about it then even if you're
thinking about it it won't be on the
right level so you need to
level so you need to
basically uh see like yes if I even if I
were to completely forget it it would
still be there but doesn't mean that you
allow yourself to yeah doesn't mean
you're already enlightened yeah exactly
that's another
way and now this other Su occurs to me
like um there a simil where somebody
walks around with a bowl of water on his
head which is like filled to the brim
and there's a big Market Square and
there's a lot of people there and other
was some enticing women to performing
some show and then there's somebody
walking behind you with a waste sword
and if there's only one drop of water
spills from that ball then that assess
will just chop your head off on the spot
and and so this ball being full of water
but can be interpreted as like you know
you you want to keep your mindfulness
and not lose it even for one drop but
that assess is again behind you right so
so mindfulness of death in that sense is
is is also a context that you can
establish um so that's also something
that you find yourself within which
which when the Sim is
can is is basically on that same level
it's not that you're creating your own
death you can die because you always
reliable to it yeah and and also as said
those were not mindful as of that in the
sense that anything that comes then it's
like it's it's
um it's like a like a Floodgate that's
open so that anything that comes in is
going to overwhelm you including most
importantly death yeah so it's um it's a
it's but see it is something that
because it doesn't depend on the content
of your experience it is actually
realistic to live with that
attitude um of of like I I must not
forget this even for a moment whereas if
it if it were about focusing you you
kind of can't do that because it's you
you won't be able to have this object
like first of all sit with your eyes
closed M every moment which is most of
the time required in order to focus on
something um but if it's this context
that stands below everything you have no
justification for losing it because you
don't need it's much more stable
actually in its nature compared to that
other direction yeah yeah and you don't
need to you don't need to forget about
what you're feeling in order to do
physical work you don't need to forget
about what you're feeling in order to
talk you don't need to forget about what
you're feeling in order to do anything M
so there isn't a justification for ever
losing that context then you can
actually then live in that way of of
perfect vigilance and
um yeah it's it's the the other thing I
wanted to clear up regarding that simile
is
is uh in the context of the like the
practice let's say when you actually sit
down and dedicate yourself to these
Reflections as as would say in seclusion
of course in an empty Hut in a in a in a
forest or something um you then have to
not take the simil lit literally in the
sense of okay let me now have this
particular thought of these Sati panas
present every second because otherwise
my head will be cut off it's that
perspective so yes you have to think
about it for a moment because it's not
like it's going to be magically there
but on its own um you have to think
about it bring it to your mind attend to
it let's say yeah and then if you saw it
properly because it is actually already
there in your experience yes sort of the
memory becomes like embedded into mhm uh
your experience then and then and then
your your goal is now okay how do I not
lose the
perspective instead of how do I just
keep this thought about the perspective
every second yeah because then you have
controlling again which is which is
maintenance and it's going to L like if
you if you're doing it that way that
kind of already implies that you didn't
see the perspective to begin with cuz it
would become obvious that that's not
where it is it's not in me thinking
about the feeling like the feeling is
not in me every second attending to the
feeling the feeling is the foundation
for my experience and I just need to
recognize it so then in that sense
mindfulness once established has to
become independent of you're doing until
it goes away and then you bring it back
and then it goes away again and then you
bring it back and so now how does it go
away because understanding how it goes
away might practically prevent it from
going away well what yeah you could say
what's the measure for it going away
yeah because if it doesn't depend on on
you thinking about it then how do we
Define when the maintenance went away
yeah that's exactly the question yes
cuz sometimes it
can go away for like could be weeks even
just like losing perspective and just
kind of like but relatively speaking
like the more subtle aspects you might
have lost but that's the good news like if
lost but that's the good news like if
you're establish in virtue some degree
of perspective will never leave you MH
that's the the the thing so yeah the
more subtle things that you're still
sort of trying to understand you might
lose those for a while but the the like
mind virtue is already a form of of
mindfulness in that sense because not
doing those things in and of itself
involves greater perspective
mhm but then yeah so actually we could
take the the example of virtue when do
you lose the mindfulness of virtue let's
say is it when like you you just forget
that that you stop repeating the Mantra
of the precepts in your mind no it's not
no when yeah yeah exactly so when you
find yourself acting out mentally
intentionally out of greed aversion or
delusion uh like let's say five H is M
that's when you know indirectly pretty
much you know indirectly sort of by
inference oh the context went away now
it's time to bring it back but for a
while you will have that there and yes
you will have like the the attempts of
the hindrances let's say but for as long
as that light of the context is there
they won't be able to find footing but
at some point it will happen that you
lost it and they will come back and then
you know oh I had to switch on the light
again yeah and um so we lose them by we
lose this perspective by not directly
but like by engaging in certain things
that require us to forget about it you
will you will find yourself in like a a
some establishment of perspective and
then something will come that feels like
it's Justified might even be like an
idea about oh let me clarify this idea
of dhama now like I know that this is
the practice right here this perspective
I know that this is actually the dhama
but my mind convinces me like no no it's
these um you know abstract scholarly
connections that I need to make between
also how does the third satiana relate
to the you know the the right livelihood
or something yeah but but but yeah but
why is that problematic because in order
to make those connections or comparisons
you you are send into the content again
I that's exactly about what say in those
words like you so you there cannot be a
comparison between backgrounds and
foregrounds from that point of view like
they they depend on one another but the
comparison that we are talking about
that makes you fall away from The
Establishment will always be that way
and then start making comparisons there
yeah so that so you so you want to go
from that horizontal view over there to
reestablish a perspective which is that
way basically um so to get into the
habit of these of of well to to get into
the habit of recognizing this tendency
to compare is useful because when you
recognize that it can help to
reestablish that perspective yeah you
you you when you're established in it
you kind of have a sense if you're
self-honest you have a sense of what
will take you away and what will not
take you away yeah and um and uh the
last thing I wanted to mention is that's
why it's the the The Virtue is necessary
beforehand because even though you might
have as the sutas would say like a
finger snap M of the right right
perspective realistically speaking if
you're not established the virtue all
these other things that will sort of
distract you from it will be so um
convincing for you like you you you're
just not used to not being trapped by
those baits that realistically speaking
that perspective is going to last very
little and then even if you're repeating
the same ideas and the same Concepts MH
you don't see the difference because
again you you you will be approaching it
through the Ang of ideas or the same
concept of okay establishing the context
but it's not in the right level now
because yeah so the idea of the context
doesn't necessarily mean that you are
now attending with the right context to
the idea of the context yeah yeah so
virtue and sens train and all these
things they just get you used to even if
you're not explicitly thinking about it
that way they get they make you get used
to not operating as much on the level of
content anymore that basically like
that's the the most direct way that you
can guarantee that when you try to
practice these these Recollections that
you won't go in the wrong direction
of terrifying ideas